William Franklin Papers 1757-1813 Mss.B.F861
American Philosophical Society
William Franklin Papers
1757-1813
Mss.B.F861
American Philosophical Society
0.25 Linear feet
The only son of Benjamin Franklin, William Franklin served as Royal Governor of New Jersey during the critical years between 1762 and 1776. An ardent Loyalist, William split with his father over their political differences in the early days of the Revolution, and after enduring two years of imprisonment, became a leader in the Loyalist cause. He settled in London in 1782, where he worked as an agent for Loyalist claims. The William Franklin Papers are a miscellaneous assemblage of letters and documents, dealing largely with Franklin's years as Royal Governor of New Jersey. The majority of the letters are perfunctory, however they provide some information on Franklin's land holdings in New Jersey and the Ohio country. The collection includes two letters relating to Franklin's imprisonment in Connecticut during the Revolution, two affectionate letters to his sister Sarah, and one to his son William Temple Franklin.
0.25 linear feet
Franklin, William, 1731-1813
Biographical/Historical note
The only son of Benjamin Franklin, William Franklin rose through life from illegitimate birth to become the last Royal Governor of New Jersey. Born in Philadelphia to an unidentified woman of low standing, William was raised by Franklin and his common law wife, Deborah Read Franklin. A favored child, he enjoyed the best education that the city could offer, including two years at Alexander Annand's classical academy, and was still in his teens when he received a commission to serve as Ensign in the 60th Regiment of Foot (the American Regiment) during King George's War. Serving in upstate New York, he distinguished himself for conspicuous bravery and won promotion to Captain of Grenadiers by the war's end, even helping his father to organize the militia in Philadelphia during a furlough in 1747.
After the war, William and his father grew increasingly close, working together on all manner of projects. William joined as an assistant in his father's electrical experiments during the 1750s, and the two worked closely in a variety of civic projects in Philadelphia. Perhaps most propitiously, William also became an important political ally in the antiproprietary faction, writing scathing pamphlets against his father's political foes under the apt pseudonym Humphrey Scourge. In return, Benjamin favored his son by using his political influence to win him appointment to a succession of minor offices, from Clerk of the Assembly to postmaster. He also served at his father's side during the Seven Years' War in organizing the colony's defenses and erecting a series of forts.
In his mid-twenties, William turned to the study of law, reading under Joseph Galloway, who later became a prominent Loyalist, and after his father's removal to London in 1757, with Richard Jackson in the Middle Temple. Ingratiating himself in London society, William earned the attention of John Pownall, Secretary of the Board of Trade, who probably recommended him for higher office. After a brief but intense struggle with the New Jersey Assembly, Pownall and the Earl of Bute had Franklin appointed Royal Governor of New Jersey in August 1762, an office he may have earned without his father's intervention.
William appointment as governor was a watershed in his career, and not merely a step up the ladder. An able administrator, his term in office began just as the colonial crises of mid-century were coming to a head. His relatively enlightened Indian policy and support for internal improvements and legal reforms, including chartering Rutgers University, were received well in the colony, however his unbending enforcement of the Stamp Act and hard line support for the government's policies earned him the disdain of American "patriots." While his father moved ever further into the revolutionary camp, William moved into the Loyalist, providing information on the revolutionary activities in the colony to London and working tirelessly against the cause for independence. After he and his father met at Galloway's estate in May 1775, the two split permanently.
Declared "an enemy to the liberties of this country" by the Continental Congress in June, 1776, William was arrested and held under harsh conditions in New Jersey and Connecticut, refusing to acknowledge to legitimacy of his captors even after being subjected to 250 days of solitary confinement. Exchanged in November 1778, Franklin entered New York, and under the direction of Henry Clinton, unleashed his efforts in the Loyalist cause. Using the formidable organizational skills associated with the Franklins, William helped found the Board of Associated Loyalists and organized Loyalist resistance activities on Long Island and northern New Jersey that were famously -- or infamously -- considered some of the most ruthless in the war. His notoriety was so great that George Washington intervened personally, though without success, in an attempt to coerce Clinton into surrendering the former governor.
With the war all but lost in August 1782, Franklin left for London. In compensation for the considerable estate he lost, he was awarded a mere £1,800 from the Commissioners of Loyalist Claims and was placed on half pay by the Army at the rank of Brigadier General. Disinherited and never fully reconciled with his father, William lived a comfortable life with his second wife, Mary D'Evelyn, a wealthy Irish widow, working as an agent for Loyalist claims.
Scope and Contents note
The William Franklin Papers are a miscellaneous assemblage of letters and documents relating to the estranged only son of Benjamin Franklin, dealing largely with his years as Royal Governor of New Jersey. The majority of the letters are perfunctory, however they provide some information on Franklin's land holdings in New Jersey and the Ohio country. The collection includes two letters relating to Franklin's imprisonment in Connecticut during the Revolution, two affectionate letters to his sister Sarah, and one to his son William Temple Franklin.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Acquired variously.
Related Archival Materials note
William Franklin appears as a correspondent and subject in the several collections to Benjamin Franklin and his family, including the Benjamin Franklin Papers (B F85), Franklin-Bache Papers (B F85ba), and the William Temple Franklin Papers (B F86).
Bibliography
Mariboe, William Herbert, The life of William Franklin, 1730(1)-1813: ''pro rege et patria" (PhD. Diss., University of Pennsylvania, 1962). Call no.: B F861ma.
Skemp, Sheila. William Franklin: Son of a Patriot, Servant of a King (New York: Oxford, 1990). Call no.: B F861s.
Stern, Randall Willard. A Little Revenge: Benjamin Franklin and His Son (Boston: Little, Brown, 1984). Call no.: B F85rn.
Early American History Note
This is a small but rich collection of William Franklin papers, most of which were written during the imperial crisis and American Revolution when Franklin served variously as royal governor of New Jersey and governor of occupied New York. The collection is a mix of official documents issued by William Franklin as governor and private correspondence with other prominent political officials, such as Joseph Galloway, speaker of colonial Pennsylvania’s Assembly and a fellow loyalist. Among his private correspondence is a series of letters written to Thomas Wharton that touch upon the Franklin family’s dealings in land speculation in Western Pennsylvania. William was involved in the New Jersey-based Burlington Land Company. There are also a few family letters William wrote to his son William Temple Franklin and Sarah Franklin Bache.
Bache, Benjamin Franklin, 1743-1808; Bache, Sarah Franklin, 1743-1808; Burr, Aaron, 1756-1836; Ferguson, Elizabeth Graeme, 1737-1801; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790; Franklin, William Temple, 1760-1823; Galloway, Joseph, 1731-1803; Hughes, John, ca.1712-1772; Wharton, Thomas, 1731-1782; American loyalists.; American Revolution; Americans Abroad; Colonial Politics; Colony and State Specific History; Family Correspondence; General Correspondence; International Affairs; Marriage and Family Life; New Jersey--History--Colonial period, ca.1600-1775; Official Government Documents and Records; Political Correspondence; United States--History--Revolution, 1775-1783
- William Franklin Papers, 1757-1813; B F861; 32 items (Box 1)
  - Letter to Betsy [Mrs. Elizabeth Graeme Ferguson], 1757 May 12; B F861.8; ALS, 1p.; Franklin, William, 1731-1813
    Scope and Contents note
    Acknowledges letters from her. Letter is framed with engravings of B. Franklin after Scheffer, Van Loo, Cochin; and Dupré medal of B.F., 1786.
    Immediate Source of Acquisition note
    Presented by Charles T. Bache; Nov. 1948.
    Bibliography
    Printed: Labaree, Papers, vol. VII, 213.
  - Letter to Joseph Galloway, 1760 June 16; B F861g; Facsimile, 3p.; Franklin, William, 1731-1813
    Relative to a pamphlet written by his father [The interest of Great Britain considered ... 1760] in answer to [William Burke's] Remarks on the Letter address'd to two great men
    General note
    FILM 54-65 FRAME 22
  - Letter to [New Jersey. General Assembly], 1763 Nov. 26; B F861.9; ALS, 1p.; Franklin, William, 1731-1813
    Instructions relative to paper currency. Sends extract of letter from General Gage.
    Photostat copy of original ms. letter, presented by W.S. Mason, Dec. 13, 1924.
  - Order to pay salary of the governor, 1764 Aug. 23; B F861.25; D.S.; New Jersey. Governor (Franklin, William)
  - An act to extend certain acts of parliament...for the preserving of all such ships and goods thereof which shall happen to be forced on shore or stranded, 1766 June 27; B F861.23; DS, 1p.; New Jersey (Oversize 1)
    William Franklin, Cortland Skinner, Speaker; Peter Kemble, Speaker, June 28, 1766.
  - Order for payment in connection with apprehension of some felons, 1766 June 28; B F861.13; ADS, 1p.; New Jersey. Governor (Franklin, William)
  - Letter to John Hughes, 1769 June 9; B F861.2; ALS, 1p.; Franklin, William, 1731-1813
    Encloses letter from B. Franklin; offers Congratulations.
    For reply to this letter, cf. Franklin Papers, V.48,137, under date of June 11, 1769.
  - Letter to "Dear Friend", 1769 Dec. 18; B F861.30; ALS, 3p.; Franklin, William, 1731-1813
    Business letter concerning Land Patents. Col. Croghan and Mr. Trent to loose their land if title not acknowledged. Mentions Mr. Wells, Joseph Morris and Philip Syng.
  - Letter to Thomas Wharton, Sr., 1769 Dec. 21; B F861.29; ALS, 3p.; Franklin, William, 1731-1813
    Friendly and business letter; concerning Galloway, Croghan, Charles Read and C. Colden.
  - Plot of Land... partly owned by Governer [sic] Franklin [Franklin Township, New York], 3 February 1770 - November 1770; B F861.27; 2.0 Item(s) 2 maps; ALS; Franklin, William Temple, 1760-1823 (Oversize 1)
    - Plan of Franklin Township containing 31,723 a[cres], 1 rod 34 p[erches] of land divided among the Proprietors into twelve lots; viz, the River-lots containing 1,860 a[cres]... each, and the back or rear lots 3,426 a[cres] each, November 1770; 1 map, 24.1 x 35.6 cm; Hooper, Robert Lettis, 1730?-1797 (Oversize 1)
      Scale: 1 inch = 100 chains.
      Other Finding Aids note
      Realms of Gold, 16 (1).
    - A Plott of a tract of 69,000 acres of land (granted Feby 3d 1770 by letters patent to Charles Reade and others) in the county of Tryon,... New York, 3 February 1770; 1 map, 47 x 37.5 cm (Oversize 1)
      The land is situated along the Susquehanna River. Annotated: "NB All the Lots on which no Quantity is mentioned contain 1000 Acres each with the usual allowance for High-Ways."
      Realms of Gold, 16 (2).
  - An act to enable persons who are his Majesty's liege subjects either by birth or naturalization to inherit and hold real estate...Council chamber, 1770 Oct. 20; B F861.17; DS; New Jersey (Oversize X)
    House of Assembly, Oct. 20,1770; Council chamber, Oct. 27,1770.
  - Letter to [Thomas Wharton, sr. ?], 1771 Jan. 5; B F861.10; Franklin, William, 1731-1813
    Land transactions; mentions Mr. [R.L.] Hooper, [George] Croghan, D. Colden, Capt. Trent, Samuel [Wharton ?], Joseph [Wharton ?], Burlington Co.
  - Order to the Treasurers...to pay his salary; Burlington, 1771 May 30; B F861.12; 1p.; New Jersey. Governor (Franklin, William)
    Printed D. filled in in ms.S: William Franklin.
  - An act for the relief of insolvent debtors, 1771 Dec. 20; B F861.24; DS, 5p.; New Jersey (Oversize 1)
    Step[he]n, Crane, Speaker, Charles Read, Scr., and W[illiam]m Franklin; Dec. 21, 1771.
  - An act for the support of government of his Majesty's colony of New Jersey... first day of October 1772... first day of October 1773 and to discharge the publick debts and contingent charges, 1772 Sept. 26; B F861.16; DS; New Jersey (Oversize 1)
    Provides for the payment of salaries of William Franklin, governor, Benjamin Franklin, agent, and others. William Franklin; Council chamber.
    Passed by the Assembly, Sept. 15, 1772, and by Council, Sept. 26, 1772. Recorded in Journal of the Provincial Council, Sept. 26, 1772 - Ricord, F.W. ed. Documents relating to the colonial history of...New Jersey, v.18,1893,349-974.9:N41.
  - Act for support of the government.., 1774 Oct. 1-1775 Oct. 1; B F861.18; DS. 3p.; New Jersey (Oversize 1)
    Provides for payment of salaries to William Franklin as governor; to Benjamin Franklin as agent; et al.
  - Order to pay Joseph Smith, for the use of Dr. Benjamin Franklin, £25 for one quarter's salary as agent for the colony of New Jersey; Perth Amboy, 1774 Nov. 16; B F861.14; Pr.DS. 1p.; New Jersey. Governor (Franklin, William)
  - Instructions on how the Governor's House at Perth Amboy should be painted and papered, 1774; B F861.28; Photostat of AD, 3p.; Franklin, William, 1731-1813
    Gift of The General Board of Proprietors of the Eastern Division of New Jersey; Feb. 1956.
  - An act to impower Isaac Haines to erect a dam, mills and other water works on the southermost branch of the Ancocas Creek in the township of Evesham in the county of Burlington, 1775 Dec. 6; B F861.20; DS.; New Jersey (Oversize 1)
  - A supplementary act to the act intitled an Act for striking 100,000£in bills of credit and directing the mode for sinking the same, 1775 Dec. 6; B F861.21; DS.; New Jersey (Oversize 1)
  - Letter to William Trent, 1776 March 14; B F861.1; ALS, 4p.; Franklin, William Temple, 1760-1823
  - Letter to William Temple Franklin, 1776 Oct. 6; B F861.6; ALS, 1p.; Franklin, William, 1731-1813
    Has hopes of being exchanged; mentions others who have been. Family news.
  - Certificate in re exchange of Gen. Silliman and other prisoners, sent to Gen. Knyphausen, 1780 Feb. 27; B F861.15; ADS, 1p. Transcribed in letter from Franklin to Gen. Silliman; March 9, 1780.; New Jersey. Governor (Franklin, William)
  - ALS to Brig. Gen. Silliman, 1780 March 9; B F861.15; ALS, 2p. Inclosing Certificate in re exchange of Gen. Silliman and other prisoners, sent to Gen. Knyphausen.; Franklin, William
  - Letter to Sarah Franklin Bache, 1782 Aug. 16; B F861.26; ALS, 1p.; Franklin, William, 1731-1813
    Forwards letter of Benjamin Franklin Bache. Presents her father's set of "Tambour Ruffles," which he believes must be Sarah's work, and takes leave of her, as he prepares to sail for England.
  - Indenture for tracts of land in the township of Franklin, Albany Co., New York, sold to W.T. Franklin for £1500; Passy, 1785 May 19; B F861.7; DS, 1p.; Franklin, William, 1731-1813 (Oversize X)
    Witnessed by Benjamin Franklin Bache and others.
    Portion of tract granted to William Franklin and others by George III, Feb. 20, 1770.
  - Indenture between William Franklin and William Temple Franklin, for purchase of lots in Burlington county, New Jersey, 1785 July 26; B F861.5; Photostat, 13p.; Franklin, William, 1731-1813
    Witnessed by B. Franklin, Benjamin Franklin Bache, and Jon. Williams.
    Presented by Charles F. Jenkins, May 1948 from original in the Secretary of State's office, Trenton, New Jersey.
  - Letter to Sarah Franklin Bache, 1792 June 30; B F861.4; ALS, 2p.; Franklin, William, 1731-1813
    Proposed visit to Preston; mentions W.T. Franklin.
  - Letter to A[aron] Burr; [London] Norton Street, [1808] Oct. 3; B F861.3; ALS, 1p.; Franklin, William, 1731-1813
    Mrs. Franklin's illness prevents his accompanying Mr. Burr to Major Gamble's.
  - Copy of will, 1813 April 15; Photostat. 4p.; Franklin, William Temple, 1760-1823
    Existence and Location of Originals note
    From a copy in the possession of Franklin Bache, 1937.
  - Card to Samuel Smith, n.d. (Tuesday evening); B F861.11; N. in 3d pers., 1p.; Franklin, William, 1731-1813
    Send books on architecture.
  - An act to authorize the Board of Justices and Freeholders of the several counties in the colony of New Jersey to defray the expence of taking lists of the inhabitants, B F861.19; DS, mutilated.; New Jersey (Oversize 1)
  - An act to enable the owners...of meadows and tide marsh lying on both sides of the south branch of Pensawkin creek in the counties of Burlington and Glocester, to erect and maintain a bank, dam and other water works across the said creek in order to prevent the tide from overflowing the same, B F861.22; D.S, mutilated.; New Jersey (Oversize 1)